<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comprehension with indulgence</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3675A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896321</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2406:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comprehension with indulgence</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154220:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Comprehenſion with Indulgence.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Nihil eſt jam dictum quod non ſuit dictum prius.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Terrence.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT hath pleaſed His Majeſty, by ſeveral Gracious Overtures, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a Union of his Proteſtant Subjects to the Conſideration of Parliament. A Deſign full of all Princely Wiſdom, Honeſty, and Goodneſs. In this Atchievement there is a double intereſt (I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend) to be diſtinguiſhed and weighed: that of <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, and that of the <hi>Nation.</hi> The advance of <hi>Religion</hi> does conſiſt much in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of its Profeſſors, both in <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> to be of one <hi>Mind,</hi> and one <hi>Heart,</hi> and one <hi>Way</hi> (in Diſcipline and Worſhip) ſo far as may be, according to the Scriptures. The advance of the <hi>Nation</hi> does lye in the Freedom and Fluoriſhing of Trade, and uniting the whole Body in the common Benefit, and dependance on the Government. The one of theſe beſpeaks an <hi>Eſtabliſhed Order</hi> and <hi>Accommodation:</hi> the other beſpeaks <hi>Indulgence, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Toleration.</hi> For, while people are in danger about Religion, we dare not launch unto into Trade (ſay they) but we muſt keep our Monies, ſeeing wee know not into what ſtreights we ſhall be driven; and when, in reference to their Party, they are held under ſeverity, it is eaſie for thoſe, who are deſigning Heads, to mould them into Wrath and Faction; which, without that occaſion, will melt, and diſſolve it ſelf into bare diſſent of Opinion, peaceably rejoycing under the enjoyment of Protection.</p>
            <p>The King, we know, is concerned, as <hi>Supreme Governour,</hi> and as a <hi>Chriſtian, Proteſtant Governour.</hi> As he is <hi>King,</hi> he is to ſeek the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Nation; as he is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the Flouriſhing of Religion: and the Proteſtant Religion particularly is his intereſt, as this Kingdom doth lie in ballance, (He being the chief Party) with its Neighbour Nations.</p>
            <p>The Judgment now of ſome is for a <hi>Comprehending Act,</hi> which may take in thoſe who are for our Parochial Churches, that Severity then might be uſed for reclaiming all whoſoever ſeparate from them: The Judgment of ſome others is, for a Free and Equal <hi>Act of Grace</hi> to all indifferently, (the Papiſt with moſt excepted) whether Separatiſts or others, abhorring <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> as more dangerous to them, upon that account mentioned, than all the Acts that have paſſed. Neither of theſe judg up to the full Intereſt of the King and Kingdom, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154220:2"/>It becomes not the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> if his Prinriples will admit him to own our Parochial Churches, and enjoy a Living, to be willing to have his Brethren, the <hi>Independent,</hi> given up to Perſecution: and it becomes not the <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> if he may but enjoy his Conſcience, to repine, or envy at the <hi>Pesbyterian</hi> for reaping any farther Emolument, ſeeing both of them (ſuppoſing the latter may do ſo) have as much at the bottom as can be, in their capacities, deſired of either. It is an Act therefore of a mixt Complection, providing both <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> for the different Parties, muſt ſerve our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And to this end (as we may humbly hope) there is a BILL at preſent in the Houſe, <hi>A BILL for the Eaſe of the Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter in the Buſineſs of Religion.</hi> Which that (upon this preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation) it may be caſt into this Model, I muſt preſent the ſame, yet in a little farther Explication.</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts (we all know) of theſe <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters.</hi> One that own the Eſtabliſhed Miniſtery, and our Pariſh-Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and are in capacity of Union upon that account, deſiring it hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily upon condeſcention to them in ſome ſmall matters: The other, that own not our Churches, and ſo are uncapable of a Conjunction, who do not, and cannot, deſire it, or ſeek it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>One,</hi> that which we propoſe is a farther latitude in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtituted Order, that ſuch may be received; and this we call <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> or <hi>Accommodation.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe, that nothing elſe were required of a Man, to be a Miniſter of a Pariſh, than there is to the Pariſhioner, to be a Member of a Pariſh-Church, as part of the National: If a perſon baptized will come to Church, and hear Common-Prayer, and receive the Sacrament, and does nothing worthy of Excommunication, he is, he may, he muſt be received for a Parochial Member: In like manner, if a Miniſter firſt ordained (and ſo <hi>Epiſcopally,</hi> or <hi>Claſſically</hi> approved in his abilities for that Function) will but read the Book of Liturgy, and adminiſter the Sacraments ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, and does nothing which deſerves Suſpenſion (we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all the indifferently ſober) why ſhould not this ſuffice a Man for the enjoying his Living, and exerciſing the Office unto which he is called?</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Other,</hi> there is indeed nothing can be done to bring thoſe in, &amp; joyn them with us in Parochial Union; yet is there this to be propoſed, that you bear with them, and not let any be <hi>Perſecuted</hi> meerly for their Conſciences; and that we call <hi>Indulgence,</hi> or <hi>Toleration.</hi> If the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> now may be <hi>Comprehended,</hi> he will be ſatisfied, to act in his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154220:2"/>without endeavouring any <hi>Alteration</hi> otherwiſe of Epiſcopacy: If the <hi>Congregationaliſt</hi> be <hi>Indulged,</hi> he will be ſatisfied, though he be not <hi>Comprehended;</hi> for that he cannot ſubmit unto, and ſo ſhall there be no Diſobligation put on any, but all be pleaſed, and enjoy the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of this <hi>BILL.</hi> Let but the Grounds of <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> be laid wide enough to take in all who can own and come into the publick Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy (which we ſuppoſe as yet to be the greater weight of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion), and when the Countenance of Authority, and all State-Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luments are caſt into one Scale, and others let alone to come of it, without Perſecution to Enflame them, or Preferment to Encourage them, (eſpecially if one expedient be uſed, which ſhall not paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned in the cloſe, that ſuch as come in may find it really better to them, to be a Prieſt to a Tribe, than a Levite to a Family,) we need not doubt but Time, the Miſtreſs of the wiſe and unwiſe, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the peaceable iſſue of ſuch Counſels.</p>
            <p>And here let me pauſe a little; for methinks I ſee what <hi>Iceſicles</hi> hang on the <hi>Eeves</hi> of the <hi>Parliament-Houſe</hi> at this Motion, what Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I mean, and Impreſſions have been laid on the Members by former Acts. There was a Speech delivered, by the then Chancellour in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Hall in <hi>Oxford,</hi> to the Parliament there, and the Scholars aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, wherein the Glory of contriving the <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of the like former Impoſitions, was moſt <hi>magnificently,</hi> as well as <hi>ſpitefully</hi> enough arrogated to its proper Author. It was, it ſeems, the deſigned Policy of that Great Man, to root thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples out of mens minds, upon which the late Wars (as he ſuppoſed) were builded, and he would do it by this invention, to wit, the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon them new <hi>Declarations, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions,</hi> of a ſtrain framed contrary to thoſe Principles. I do remember now the Sentence of <hi>Eſdras</hi> to the Apologue of the Anglel, where the <hi>Woods</hi> and the <hi>Seas</hi> would encounter one another. <hi>Verily</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it was a fooliſh puopoſe;</hi> for the Trees could not come down from the Hills, nor the Waves get up from the Shoars. I muſt ſay the ſame of this Policy. It was really a great vanity to think that Folks ſhould be made to ſwear away their Thoughts and Beliefs. Whatſoever it is we think or believe, we do think it, we muſt think it, we do believe it, we muſt believe it, notwithſtanding any of theſe outward Impoſitions. The honeſt man indeed will refuſe an Injunction againſt his Conſcience, the Knave will ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, but both retain their <hi>Principles;</hi> which the laſt will be the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt to put any villanous <hi>Practice.</hi> On the contrary, there is nothing could be adviſed more certain, to keep the Covenant, and ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154220:3"/>alive in mens hearts, and memories, than this perpetual enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Renunciation</hi> of it. Nor may you wonder, if that Leſſon ſink deep into mens fleſh, which you will teach them with <hi>Briars</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> as <hi>Gideon taught</hi> the men of <hi>Succoth.</hi> Beſides, it is the moſt unpolitick thing that ever could have been, for ſuch Contents, as are of that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence to Majeſty and the Government, to have them once diſputed, or brought into queſtion, to be put into theſe Declarations, Oaths and Subſcriptions, which neceſſitates the examination of them to ſo many. It was the Wiſdom of the ancient Church, inſtead of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about the Jewiſh Ceremonies, to take care they might have an honourable Burial: and I dare ſay, if that Great Lord Chancellour had but put off his Cap to the Covenant, and bidden it a fair adieu only, he ſhould have done more towards its Extirpation, than by all this ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated trouble to mens Conſciences. And if it ſhall therefore pleaſe the ſucceeding <hi>Miniſters</hi> of our <hi>State,</hi> inſtead of going to root out the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Innovation</hi> which are got into people, by this means (which is no means to do it, but the means to rivet them more in us), to endeavour rather, to root out the <hi>Cauſes</hi> from us, which make men willing to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch Principles, and deſire change: I ſuppoſe their Policy will prove the ſounder. The way to eſtabliſh the Throne of the King is this, to make it appear, that all thoſe <hi>Grievances,</hi> and all thoſe <hi>Good things</hi> which the people in the late times expected to be <hi>removed,</hi> or to be <hi>obtained,</hi> by a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or a change of the Government, may be more effectually accompliſhed by a King in the Acts of his Parliament.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible how my Theme riſes upon me, and that I begin to ſhoot wide: I take my aim therefore again, and two things, in earneſt, I would expect from this BILL, as the ſum of what is neceſſary to the <hi>End</hi> of it, our <hi>Eaſe,</hi> if it be made to ſerve the turn. The one is, that Biſhop <hi>Land</hi> be confined to his Cathedrals: and the other, that Chancellour <hi>Hyde</hi> be totally expell'd our Acts of Parliament. By the <hi>firſt,</hi> I mean, that the Ceremonies in the ordinary Pariſh-Churches be left to the liberty of the Miniſter, to uſe, or uſe them not, according to his Conſcience, and Prudence toward his own Congregation: and by the <hi>latter,</hi> that all theſe new deviſed <hi>Oaths, Subſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> together with the <hi>Canonical Oath,</hi> and the <hi>Subſcription</hi> in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons be ſuſpended for the time to come. If that be too much, I ſhall content my ſelf with a modeſter Motion, that whatſoever theſe <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> be, that are required to be <hi>Made, Subſcribed,</hi> or <hi>Sworn,</hi> they may be impoſed only as to the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> leaving the Takers but free to the uſe of their own Expreſſions. And this Expedient I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154220:3"/>from my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> who hath providently, as it were, againſt ſuch a ſeaſon, laid in this Obſervation. <hi>The form of the Subſcription ſet down in the Cannons, ratified by King</hi> James, <hi>was not expreſſed in the Act of the Thirteenth of</hi> Elizabeth. <hi>Inſtit. p.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 74. And conſequently, if the Clergy enjoyed this Freedom until then, in reference to the particulars therein contained, what hinders why they might not have the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, in reference alſo to others?</p>
            <p>It is true, that it may ſeem hard to many in the Parliament, to <hi>undo</hi> any thing themſelves have <hi>done:</hi> but though this be no <hi>Rule</hi> for <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who are ſometimes to <hi>repent</hi> as well as <hi>believe,</hi> if they be loath to <hi>Repeal</hi> any thing, what if they ſhall only <hi>Interpret</hi> or <hi>Explain?</hi> Let us ſuppoſe then ſome Clauſe in this BILL, or ſome new Act, for <hi>Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</hi> If any Nonconformiſt cannot come up to the full meaning and intent of theſe Injunctions rightly explained, let him remain <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> under the ſtate only of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> without benefit of <hi>Comprehenſion;</hi> for ſo long as thoſe who are not <hi>Comprehended,</hi> may yet enjoy that <hi>Eaſe</hi> as to be <hi>Indulged</hi> in ſome equal meaſure anſwerable to his Majeſties Declaration, whether <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> be large or narrow, ſuch terms as we obtain are pure advantage, and ſuch as we obtain not, are no loſs: But if any does, and can honeſtly agree to the whole Senſe the Parliament intends in ſuch Impoſitions, why ſhould there be any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for ſuch a man, though he delivers himſelf in his own Words, to be received into the eſtabliſhed Order with others? Unleſs men will look on theſe Injunctions only to be contrived for <hi>Engines of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> to deſtroy the Nonconformiſt: and not as <hi>Inſtruments of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> to edifie the Church of God.</p>
            <p>I will not leave our <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren neither, ſo long as I have ſomething more that may be ſaid for them, not ordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by any. It is this, that though indeed they are not, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſeek to be of our Churches as they are <hi>Parochial,</hi> under the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> or <hi>Superintendency</hi> of the Biſhops: yet do they not refuſe, but ſeek to be comprehended within the Church as <hi>National</hi> under His Majeſty. I will explain my ſelf. The Church may be conſidered <hi>as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and ſo Chriſt alone is the Head of it, and we receive our Laws from him: or <hi>as Particular,</hi> and ſo the Paſtors are Heads, Guides, or Biſhops over their reſpective Flocks, who are commanded therefore <hi>to obey them in the Lord:</hi> or <hi>as National,</hi> which is an accidental and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal reſpect to the Church of God, wherein the King is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Supreme Head of it, and as I judg no otherwiſe: For thus alſo runs the Statute, <hi>That our Soveraign Lord ſhall be taken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154220:4"/>the only Supreme Head in Earth of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>called</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Anglicana. Now if it ſhould pleaſe the King and Parliament, to allow and approve theſe <hi>Separate Meetings,</hi> and <hi>Stated places for Worſhip,</hi> by a Law, as His Majeſty did by his Declaration, I muſt profeſs that, as ſuch Aſſemblies by this means muſt be conſtituted immediately <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral parts</hi> of the Church as National, no leſs than our Pariſh-Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſo would the Congregate Churches (at leaſt thoſe that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelves) own the King for Head over them, in the ſame ſenſe as we own him Head over ours, that is as much as to ſay, for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme <hi>Coercive</hi> Governour of all (in this accidental regard), both to keep every ſeveral Congregation to that Goſpel-Order themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs: and to ſuperviſe their Conſtitutions in things indifferent, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done but in Subordination to the Peace of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Well, let us ſuppoſe then a Liberty for theſe Separate Aſſemblies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Viſitation of His Majeſty and his Juſtices, and not the Biſhops; I would fain know what were the Evil you can find in them. If it lie in any thing, it muſt be in that you call <hi>Schiſm.</hi> Separation then let us know, in it ſelf ſimply conſidered, is nothing, neither good nor evil. There may be reaſon to <hi>divide,</hi> or <hi>ſeparate</hi> ſome Chriſtians from others out of Prudence, as the <hi>Catechumens</hi> of old from the <hi>fully instructed,</hi> for their greater Edification; and as a Chappel or two is added to a Pariſh-Church when the People elſe were too big a Congregation. It is not all <hi>Diviſion</hi> then or <hi>Separation</hi> is Schiſm: but <hi>ſinful Diviſion.</hi> Now the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority as National Head, having appointed the Parochial Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and required all the Subjects of the Land to frequent them, and them alone, for the acknowledging, glorifying, or National ſerving and worſhipping the one only true God, and his Son, whom we have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received: and this Worſhip or Service, in the nature of it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally good, and the external Order (ſuch as that of Time and Place, and the like Circumſtances) being properly under his Juriſdiction, it hath ſeemed to me hitherto, that unleſs there was ſomething in that Order or Way preſcribed which is ſinful, and that required too as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of that Communion, there is no man could refuſe his attendance on theſe Parochial Aſſemblies, without the ſin of Diſobedience; and conſequently his Separation thereby becoming ſinful, proves <hi>Schiſm:</hi> but if the Scene be altered, and theſe ſeparate Aſſemblies made <hi>Legal,</hi> the Schiſm, in reference to the National Church, upon the ſame account, does vaniſh. Schiſm is a Separation from that Church whereof we <hi>ought</hi> or are <hi>bound</hi> to be members: if the Supreme Authority then looſe our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to the Pariſh-Meeting, ſo that we are bound no longer, the <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154220:4"/>(I ſay, upon this account) is <hi>not to be found,</hi> and the Schiſm gone. Lo here, a way opened for the Parliament (if they pleaſe) to rid the trouble and ſcruple of Schiſm (at once) out of the Land. If they pleaſe not, yet is there ſomething to be thought on for the Separatiſt in a way of <hi>Forbearanee;</hi> that the innocent Chriſtian, at leaſt, as it was in the time of <hi>Trajan,</hi> may not be <hi>ſought out unto Puniſhment:</hi> Eſpecially when ſuch a <hi>Toleration</hi> only is deſired, as is conſiſtent with the <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> a <hi>Good Life,</hi> and the <hi>Government of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I turn me to the Houſes. My Lords and Gentlemen! I will ſuppoſe you honeſt Perſons, that would do as you would be done unto; that would not wrong any, or if you did, would make them recompence. There hath been very hard Acts paſſed, which when the bills were brought in, might haply look ſmooth and faire to you: but you ſaw not the covert art, ſecret machination, and purpoſely contrived ſnares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one whole party. If ſuch a form of words would not, another ſhould do their buſineſs. By this means, you in the firſt place your ſelves ſome of you were overſtript: Multitudes diſpoſſeſt of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings: The Vineyard let out to others: The Lord Jeſus the Maſter of it, deprived of many of his faithful Labourers: And the poor ſheep (what had they done) bereft of their accuſtomed ſpiritual food, to the hazard of their eternal Souls. Among many Arguments therefore for Liberty in other Papers, from <hi>Policy, Convenience, Reaſon of State,</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Religion,</hi> I have this one to offer you of a more binding nature, an Argument from <hi>Juſtice, Rigtheouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution</hi> to the Diſplaced. It is true, that the Places they once had are filled, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: but there are others enough. There are many of thoſe who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs <hi>theirs,</hi> do alſo keep their <hi>own,</hi> and keep <hi>more.</hi> There are many, who are <hi>Canons, Deans, Prebendaries,</hi> that are alſo <hi>Parſons, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Vicars;</hi> who have Benifices and Honours by Heaps, and by the Buſhel. If it ſhall pleaſe You therefore in this BILL on the Anvil, or in another, to take cognizance of <hi>Pluralities,</hi> that for the preventing an idle, ſcandalous, covetouſly overgrown, unprofitable Miniſtery, every man who hath more than one Cure of Souls, or one Dignity, ſhall give them up into a publick ſtock, or to a general Diſtribution, you ſhall do the Church right, and the Ejected right, you ſhall give ſuch Drones their due, and God his due, and ſtrew the way by this meanes for the making your <hi>Grace</hi> intended in this Bill, of ſignification. In the name of God Sirs, let me move you to this, if it were only <hi>Hac Vice,</hi> for a preſent need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conjunction of us at this ſeaſon. We ſee the jawes of Popery and the Sectary opening upon us, if the ſober Proteſtant intereſt be not united,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154220:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>we periſh. I know who will be ready to ſtamp here and throw duſt in the Air, for it is theſe <hi>Sons of the Horſe-leech</hi> whoſe voice is ſtill <hi>Give Give</hi> that will never be contented with a <hi>ſingle Portion.</hi> A <hi>Dignity</hi> therefore with a <hi>Living,</hi> let them be allowed: but one <hi>Dignity</hi> and one <hi>Cure of Souls</hi> ſhould be all, though they <hi>cut themſelves with Lances.</hi> It is this damn'd hard objection at the bottom, the Prieſts covetouſneſs and corruption, rather than their diſpute about things indifferent, that really hinders the Churches Peace and Proſperity.</p>
            <p>To conclude. According to what every mans mind is moſt upon (the Publick intereſt, or his Own), ſuch is his value more or leſs.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
